Finding Aid for the Paul Dell Collection of Documents Pertaining to IBRO (International Brain Research Organization) Biomed.0142
UCLA Library Special Collections
Paul Dell collection of documents pertaining to IBRO (International Brain Research Organization)
1961-1972
UCLA Library Special Collections
Dell, Paul Charles
Biomed.0142
1 Linear Feet (1 carton)
Internationally known and respected neuroscientist Paul Charles Dell, M.D., was intimately connected with the founding and growth of the International Brain Research Organization (IBRO), an independent non-governmental organization with UNESCO affiliation. This collection covers IBRO documents and correspondence from 1961 to 1972, with the bulk from 1969 to 1971, the years in which Professor Dell was its Executive Secretary. Included are minutes and reports of IBRO governing bodies and committees and a great deal of correspondence.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Acquisition Information
The collection was deposited in the UCLA Neuroscience History Archives, which transferred it to History & Special Collections for the Sciences, UCLA Library Special Collections, in 2013.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9973749873606533
Biography
Paul Dell, M.D. (1915-1976) was an internationally respected neurophysiologist whose major research focused on the brainstem reticular formation and its autonomic and humoral regulatory mechanisms. After graduation from the Faculty of Medicine, Strasbourg, he served as an army doctor in 1939-1940. After four years of physiological research in Lyon he joined the Faculty of Medicine in Strasbourg. 1949-1950 saw him in Chicago working with Warren McCulloch and Horace W. Magoun, and in 1951 he returned to Paris to join the C.N.R.S., where he rose to be Director of Research. In 1967 he moved to the Division of Neurobiological Research of I.N.S.E.R.M. in Marseille, to become its director.
Dr. Dell was one of a group of neuroscientists who, through discussions at the newly founded International Federation of Societies for Electroencephalography and Clinical Neurophysiology, and at the important Colloquium of Electroencephalography and Higher Nervous Activity (known as the "Moscow Colloquium") in 1958, articulated the need for a multidisciplinary organization to facilitate international collaboration and communication in basic brain research, and presented a resolution to form such a body. These discussions and resolution led eventually to the formation of the International Brain Research Organization (IBRO). The first governing body of IBRO met in Paris in 1960, and the association was incorporated in 1961 as an independent non-government organization affiliated with UNESCO. (An excellent early history of IBRO was published in "Neuroscience" 72(1):283-306, 1996).
Dr. Dell was active in the formation of IBRO, and he served the organization faithfully until the end of his life. He was part of the original governing council, co-organized an early IBRO-sponsored symposium in 1962 (The Neurochemical Regulators of Brain Activity), was appointed Deputy Executive Secretary in 1962 for a time, and served as Executive Secretary from 1969 to 1971. He also was a consultant for brain research to UNESCO for many years, and advised IBRO on its relationship with UNESCO. He was one of the founding members, and an editor in neurophysiology, of the journal "Experimental Brain Research".
Scope and Content
The collection consists entirely of documents and correspondence related to the founding and growth of IBRO (International Brain Research Organization), an independent non-governmental organization with UNESCO affiliation. Included are minutes and reports of IBRO governing bodies and committees and a great deal of correspondence. The bulk of the material dates from 1969 to 1971, the years when Dr. Paul Dell was Executive Secretary; the outgoing correspondence from his office during those years may be represented in its entirety. For the earlier years there are fewer letters and reports, but the activities of the Executive Committee and the Central Council are well covered. The names and contents of the folders are those of the original binders.
Related Material
UCLA Biomedical Library History and Special Collections for the Sciences, Manuscript Collection #143, "Heinrich Waelsch collection of documents pertaining to IBRO" contains similar [and sometimes overlapping] documents and correspondence, for 1961-1965.
Societies, Scientific -- Collected Correspondence; Societies, Medical -- Collected Correspondence; Neuroscientists -- Archival resources; Neurosciences -- History; International Brain Research Organization -- History; Dell, Paul Charles -- Archives
- IBRO Statutes and By-Laws., 1961. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Revised Edition, printed 1962 by UNESCO
- Restructuring of IBRO and revised Statutes and By-Laws., 1968-1970. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  transcript of initial Central Council meeting; notes discussing new structure of IBRO and by-law revisions; letters of comments and suggestions; approved version of new statutes and by-laws
- Symposium on "The Neurochemical Regulators of Brain Activity"., 1961. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  correspondence re. a small symposium sponsored by IBRO and organized by Professors Paul Dell and Herbert Jasper
- IBRO Executive Committee and Central Council., 1964-1965. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- IBRO Executive Committee and Central Council., 1966. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- IBRO Executive Committee and Central Council., 1967. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- IBRO Executive Committee and Central Council., 1968. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- IBRO Executive Committee and Central Council., 1969. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- IBRO Executive Committee and Central Council., 1970. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  correspondence; Committee reports
- IBRO Executive Committee and Central Council., 1971. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  correspondence; minutes of IBRO Working Group on Brain Research and Working Paper no. I: IBRO Activities (1961-1971)/ Future Plans; Central Council minutes
- IBRO finances., 1968-1972. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  mainly correspondence with Donald B. Lindsley, IBRO Treasurer, 1969-1972
- IBRO Central Council Sub-Committee on Symposia., 1961-1971. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Symposium Program review, with listing of symposia, 1961-1971; Committee reports, 1967-1971; general Committee correspondence; correspondence concerning specific symposia
- IBRO Central Council Sub-Committee on Education., 1961-1971.; folder 1 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  report on the Workshop Program, 1961-1971, listing workshops; Committee reports, 1968-1970; general Committee correspondence
- IBRO Central Council Sub-Committee on Education., 1968-1970.; folder 2 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  correspondence, participants lists, and reports, for: 1. "Neurochemical and Neuroendocrinological Methods in Brain Research" Visiting Workshop, Karachi, Pakistan, 1968; 2. "Neurophysiological Techniques Related to Behavior", Visiting Workshop, Kotor, Yugoslavia, 1969; 3. "Synaptic Mechanisms" Visiting Workshop, Kiev, USSR, 1970
- IBRO Central Council Sub-Committee on Grants and Fellowships., 1958-1970. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Committee reports; correspondence and reports on fellowships, travel grants, and temporary research teams
- The Application of Brain Research to Problems in Education and Social Sciences., 1968--1971. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  reports and correspondence of an interdepartmental committee tasked with planning IBRO's projects and contributions to an UNESCO program; correspondence and reports of various expert working groups
- IBRO Bulletin., 1967-1970. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  correspondence and reports
- IBRO external relationships - national and international brain research organizations., 1969-1971.; folder 1 of 3 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  correspondence
- IBRO external relationships - UNESCO, WHO., 1968-1970.; folder 2 of 3 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  official documents; correspondence
- IBRO external relationships - ICRO (International Cell Research Organization)., 1963-1972.; folder 3 of 3 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  activity reports
- Correspondence., 1969-1971.; folder 1 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  general incoming letters, most with replies
- Correspondence., 1968-1971.; folder 2 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  carbon copies of outgoing correspondence, bulk for 1969
  General note
  some duplication with other folders
- Obituaries., 1977. (Box 1, Folder 23)